GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
Hugo Strange can fix Butch.
Strange might be
my only hope, Tabby.
But whatever happens
after I walk out that door,
I care about you.
And I always will.
JEREMIAH: Jerome
is dead. Long live me.
Oh, my God!
I have bombs planted
around this city.
GORDON: These are the buildings
Jeremiah's planning to demolish
with his bombs.
Once those buildings are blown,
they collapse and create
the labyrinth from
the finished drawing.
GORDON: I have the locations
of every bomb Jeremiah planted.
How did they beat you, huh?
I'll have to start again.
I had a vision of
Gotham in flames.
Together we can
make that happen.
Now listen closely
to what you must do.
Come on, Selina.
(ALFRED GRUNTS)
It's okay, it's okay.
Make way.
We'll do everything we can.
But the evacuation has us
dealing with a skeleton crew.
Bruce...
Selina, you're at the hospital.
You're gonna be okay.
Are you gonna leave me?
No, I'm gonna be right here.
(VOICE BREAKING) Promise?
I promise.
(RATTLING)
You know, I don't know
why I brought him here.
I should've killed him
when I had the chance.
You did the right thing, Alfred.
You say that. You didn't
see what he did to Selina.
All right, I better
get to the hospital.
I'll stop by when I can.
Alfred.
Couldn't have put a cap in that
psycho and done the world a favor?
Where are we?
Bomb squad's at the
last site on the map.
After they disarm the bomb,
they're gonna put it in the warehouse
with all the others.
Also, the Mayor called. He
wants to lift the evacuation order.
Tell him we are not doing
anything until we have
all the bombs locked away.
Pardon me, Jim.
Don't you all have work to do?
What is it?
I'd like to press charges
against Bruce Wayne's butler.
I mean, just look at my face.
I think you look great.
And I'd like to
speak to Bruce again.
We couldn't really talk before
what with his girlfriend bleeding out
all over him.
You tried to prove you're
better than your brother.
But I'm still here.
The city's still here.
You're a failure, Jeremiah.
Enjoy Arkham. Your brother did.
Put him in the box. Get
him ready for transport.
Bring me Bruce Wayne
and I'll tell you where
the other bombs are.
We have all your bombs.
The maze bombs, yes.
I mean the other ones.
Jim, as an engineer,
you expect systems to fail.
So, you build in redundancies.
And I am a very good engineer.
- You're bluffing.
- Am I?
How many lives are
you willing to bet?
You're right, you
know. I did fail.
I didn't yet understand the
vision I was servicing, but,
I do now. My eyes are
open as will yours be.
When you realize I'm not
bluffing, bring me Bruce Wayne.
And I'd like a coffee.
Black. Two sugars.
(EKG FLATLINING)
No heartbeat.
Extraordinary.
This better work.
The chemicals that turned
him into this beautiful specimen
kept his organs
surprisingly well-preserved.
Once we flush his
body with anti-toxins,
we'll top him off with
some fresh blood.
And a quick jolt to the heart
will see him good as new.
You hear that?
You're gonna be cured.
- Yeah.
- (CELL PHONE RINGING)
What?
When?
- What is it?
- (GASPS)
Selina's been shot by
that lunatic Jeremiah.
She's at Gotham General.
I have to go. I'll be back.
Of course. You go
check on the kid.
What? No, she's in surgery.
I'm gonna kill Jeremiah.
- (GUN COCKING)
- I'm coming with you.
I don't advise that. The
procedure should not be interrupted.
(GROANING)
TABITHA: Stay.
I'll be here. Making sure
everything goes as planned.
I'm doing this for
Butch. Not for you.
It's okay.
Unfortunately,
there's no telling
just how many battery
bombs Jeremiah produced.
He was fanatically secretive
about his technology
and Bruce trusted him, so...
He's gotta be bluffing.
Yeah.
Cap, Mayor's on the phone again.
The evacuation stays in effect.
I will tell him when it's lifted.
LUCIUS: You think
there are more bombs?
Up till now, Jeremiah's actions
sprang from the fear and hatred
of his brother.
Even his obsession with Bruce
is just a reflection of Jerome's.
What did he mean when
he said he didn't understand
the vision he was serving?
That his eyes had been opened.
BURKE: Perhaps the previous
mayor took orders from a police captain.
- Captain Gordon...
- Jim Gordon is not the Mayor
of Gotham, I am.
The people need to know the
city is safe. I'm lifting the order.
What are you looking at?
There's a man on the building
across the street, staring at us.
What?
(WHINING)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
How many bombs are
there? Where are they?
I want to talk to Bruce Wayne.
Tell me where they
are, you son of a bitch.
Who's helping you?
Bruce Wayne.
(GORDON GRUNTS)
You are never gonna
talk to Bruce Wayne.
You hear me?
Then more people will die.
Well, you never were good at
holding on to what you care about,
were you, James?
Jim, we need you out here now!
(HUMMING SOFTLY)
Can I help you?
Captain Gordon? Major Rodney
Harlan, Seventh Division, Fort Henry.
Major, I assume you're here
to help with the evacuation.
If so, Detective
Bullock can coordinate.
The Governor has
declared martial law.
Until this crisis is
resolved, I'm in charge here.
Are you serious?
Son, this is not
a pissing match.
I was sent here to restore
order in a chaotic situation.
Can I count on you?
- Yes, sir.
- What do we got?
Not much. Valeska
had a plan to knock down
a number of buildings in Gotham.
We recovered those bombs,
but he's stashed away more.
Who's helping him?
Somebody's gotta be.
It's unclear. We've
heard reports that
his followers have
turned on him,
which would indicate
he has someone else.
He would like to talk to Bruce
Wayne. That's clearly a trap.
His brother pulled the same gag.
There was a blimp,
it was a whole thing.
We'll make sure he's
safe. Get me Bruce Wayne.
Major, you cannot bring
Bruce Wayne down...
Not your call, Captain.
- Now.
- Yes, sir.
You have no idea
who you're dealing with.
Arrest Captain Gordon.
(ALL MURMURING)
Hey, are you out of
your freakin' mind?
You listen to me. This city
is holding on by a thread.
I would not allow anything
to jeopardize it further.
Including insubordination.
Escort Captain
Gordon across the river.
Hold him there till
you hear from me.
Get me Bruce Wayne.
(MUFFLED GUNSHOTS)
I strike where you lie.
Death's gentle cousin.
The answer is sleep, Ed...
It's polite to let
people finish.
Rise and shine!
Good morning, sweetheart.
I know. Waking up in
the Narrows, a prisoner.
Must feel like history
repeating itself.
Ed.
Speaking of history, remember
when you punched me in the face?
(GRUNTING)
That felt good.
Listen to me. Jeremiah
Valeska has more bombs.
- You have to...
- I have to what, Jim?
Set you free?
Help save the city?
Well, we've been there,
done that. And guess what?
Shocker! Lee and
I are still fugitives.
I offered her a way out.
Oh, by returning the money?
She's dispersed that among
all the deadbeats of the Narrows.
Not exactly what I
would have done.
But, point is, it's gone.
Now, on with the show.
We're a little pressed for time.
(NYGMA LAUGHING)
Ed, Ed, Ed...
Wait. Ed. Wait, wait, Ed.
- This is 50 pounds of pressure.
- (GRUNTING)
What are you doing?
(IN FRENCH) Peine forte et dure.
Was my own version of it anyway.
You see in the old days, they used
to pile weights on a prisoner's chest.
Tried to get a confession.
Usually, they just died.
- That's 100 pounds.
- (GROANING)
Why?
To help Lee break
free from her history.
You see, she has this anchor,
deadweight holding her to her past,
and that's you.
Once you're gone, she'll
finally be free to be the person
she was meant to be.
The person I want her to be.
- (WHIRRING)
- (GROANING)
- 150.
- (GRUNTING)
You see, I saw you together. I
saw the way she looked at you.
So, for her sake,
you're gonna die.
And for my sake,
you're gonna suffer.
(GRUNTING)
Now, this is gonna
be so much fun.
(LAUGHING)
This evacuation is going to
leave a lot of territory undefended.
Shame not to capitalize.
(GRUNTING)
Hello, Barbara.
Was only hoping to talk.
By attacking my people?
- Call it precaution.
- What do you want?
I'm leaving Gotham and I
want you to come with me.
(SCOFFS) Try again.
I had a vision when I took
back the Demon's Head.
Death. Destruction.
The city in flames.
But it didn't come to be.
How disappointing for you.
Indeed, for many reasons.
Not least is that for centuries I
have depended on the Demon's head
to get ahead of my enemies.
But, without the full
measure of its power...
Wait. Are you saying you think
some of it might still be in me?
Interesting. So I guess
you're here to kill me for it.
You misunderstand.
Remember the woman from the
tapestry, the one whose features you share?
The whore you murdered?
How could I forget?
I lied. To get under your skin.
I loved her. Very much.
I offered her eternity,
but she turned it down.
And now, I make
you the same offer.
Join me. And we will rule the
League of Shadows together.
Think about it.
What about your
vision? The city on fire.
I am making certain
of it even now.
Its destruction will give rise
to the one I foresaw long ago.
The one who brought
me here, my heir.
Bullock, can you tell this
putz to let us go, please?
Major, the men escorting
Gordon were attacked.
Your guys didn't see who. I'm
thinking it's either Valeska's...
Enough. Did you prepare
Valeska like I asked?
Yeah.
Mr. Wayne, you'll
be perfectly safe.
If you could help us learn
the location of the bombs...
Major, you brought
me here against my will.
I want to go back to the
hospital and back to my friend.
Let's get this over with.
Hello, Bruce.
It's great to see you.
Where are the bombs, Jeremiah?
Closer, please.
Closer.
Tell me. How is the
young lady doing?
You know why we're
destined to be best friends?
Because we're very much
alike. You are as I used to be.
At war with your true nature.
You must truly embrace it
if you ever want to be free.
I'm just trying to help you.
Trying to help me?
By torturing Alfred?
Trying to destroy Gotham?
By shooting Selina?
You think we're alike because
there's a darkness inside both of us.
But the difference is, I
know how to control mine.
I think you could be so strong.
I see it.
He sees it too.
What do you mean, "he"?
Ask him about the bombs.
Where are the other bombs?
What bombs?
Bombs you planted
around the city.
You blew up the Mayor.
Ah, that bomb. Yes,
that was the only one.
But it did what it had to do.
It got you here.
All right, that's enough.
I want my boy out, mate.
- Mmm-mmm.
- You said, "he."
Who do you mean?
The one who opened up my eyes.
Who showed me that
everything I was doing,
was not to create a
Gotham of my own.
But yours.
The Gotham you need.
Your dark island. And
it will come to be, Bruce.
Tonight.
Tell me his name.
What did the doctors say?
Will the little bitch
ever walk again?
What vertebrae did I sever?
I was hoping for the lumbar...
Tell me his name!
You already know his
name. You're his heir.
Ra's al Ghul.
- No, it can't...
- Shh.
(MAN SCREAMS)
MAN: Bullock? HARVEY: Yeah.
(WHIRRING)
- 350 pounds of pressure.
- (GRUNTS)
Getting hard to breathe?
- I'll take that as a yes.
You know, if we listen carefully,
we can hear some ribs cracking soon.
(LAUGHING)
Four hundred fifty.
Healthy male adult. His ribs should
be able to take about 450 pounds
- before they crack.
- (GROANS)
Do you think you could
hide this from me, Ed?
I'm Queen of the Narrows.
People tell me things.
I know how this looks.
It looks like you're trying
to crush him to death
because you think we still
have feelings for each other.
Well, perhaps we should
jump to why this is a good thing.
I can't wait.
He's holding you back.
From?
From being the person
that you are meant to be.
The woman that I love.
(SIGHS) You really
think so little of me?
I don't follow that.
How weak would that person need to
be if Jim Gordon could hold her back?
It's actually insulting.
That's not what I intended, I...
Enough.
Yesterday, you said a part of
you would always care for me.
The woman you loved
is gone. Understand?
Yes.
The Narrows is free
from landlords and gangs.
Every family has money to build
their life. I'm done. I'm leaving.
I want you to come with me.
But if you kill Jim, don't bother.
And I will decide
who I'm going to be.
Not you. Not Jim Gordon. Me.
I'm leaving tonight.
It's your choice.
(DOOR CLOSES)
She chose me, Jim.
Did you hear that?
It's all I wanted.
You can have Gotham.
(GRUNTS)
BARBARA: By the time I got
there, Jeremiah had already escaped.
ALFRED: Right. Where
the hell is Ra's al Ghul?
Alfred. Let me guess. Ra's
helped Jeremiah kidnap Bruce.
So you came to me to find Ra's.
Would you care to
tell me where he is?
I don't know where he is. But
I know where he's gonna be.
Ra's is leaving Gotham tonight
after turning it to a pile of rubble.
With, I assume, Jeremiah's
help. So, here's the deal.
You get to kill Jeremiah,
you get to rescue Bruce,
and I get to kill Ra's.
And how do you plan
on doing that then?
I got a little surprise for him.
PENGUIN: One question.
Who do I get to kill?
The only way to keep
Butch on the table
was to promise I
would come help.
Well.
Don't we make
quite the little gang?
Let's do this.
- (GROANING)
- (SIREN WAILING)
Hey.
My car's around the corner.
You're gonna
wanna ice those ribs.
Is it true about you
leaving Gotham?
- Yes.
- And taking Ed with you?
That's none of your concern.
Back in the GCPD,
when I told you there was
so much I wish I could change,
- you asked me what I meant.
- Jim.
I would change everything
that brought us to this point.
I would ask you to leave Gotham
with me that first moment I saw you
and I would make sure
we had a life together.
Then you wouldn't be you.
Maybe that'd be a good thing.
No, it wouldn't.
I'm not going back to who I was.
But, what you said yesterday about
part of you always caring for me,
I feel the same way.
Goodbye. Now, go save Gotham.
Ready at your command, Major.
- Jim.
- Harvey.
Thank God, you're all right.
What the hell happened?
It's a long story. Did Harlan
get Bruce to the precinct?
Yeah, it's bad.
- What are you talking about?
- (SIGHS)
Jeremiah escaped. He's got
Bruce. He took the bombs, all of them.
It's true.
- How did you two...
- Find each other?
I'd like to think it
was you, Bruce.
You brought us together.
I trust things went smoothly?
Like clockwork.
Did your men retrieve my bombs?
They are en route to their
positions as we speak.
From here,
we can take in the full
majesty of Gotham's destruction.
You're both insane.
I know it's difficult
to fathom, Bruce.
But Jeremiah and I are
doing this for your benefit.
How is destroying Gotham
supposed to help me?
Because I had a vision.
That out of this
crucible of blood and fire
will rise the Dark Knight that
your city needs. That I need.
To be honest, Bruce.
Prophesies, visions.
Not really my cup of tea.
But our friend revealed
something to me.
That my twin obsessions,
rebuilding Gotham and rebuilding you,
are one and the same.
You're the brother I never had.
The one Jerome never could be.
We will create a
legacy in this city.
Gotham falls. We rise.
Together.
A dozen transport vans were
stolen from the GCPD motor pool.
That's gotta be how
they're carrying the bombs.
There were sightings
here, here and here.
They're moving towards
the outskirts of Gotham.
Jeremiah must have
changed targets.
- Gordon.
- Perfect.
You have some explaining to
do. What happened to my men?
Major, we got
serious fish to fry...
I didn't ask for your
opinion, Detective.
Two more sightings.
Bolyston and Third,
and they're moving north
along the Van Hook Highway.
That doesn't make any sense.
What buildings would
he be targeting there?
Told me Jeremiah promised to
turn Gotham into a dark island.
We need to cancel the evacuation.
Get those people off the bridges.
Absolutely not.
They're filled with
people leaving the city.
We bring them back into
Gotham. Buildings fall...
The bridges are the targets.
Harper, spread the word.
Don't move. Arrest
Captain Gordon.
I wouldn't do that.
Arrest them both.
Officer, your radio.
This is Captain Gordon. I want
all the bridges cleared immediately.
I repeat. Clear all the bridges.
Civilization, so fragile, Bruce.
Gotham is soon to be each man
for himself, a more savage place.
Sounds like fun.
Sure you wanna leave?
Oh, hey, Bruce. Freak.
Hello, Barbara. I'm
really glad you came.
(SIGHS) Bad news,
baby. I'm not leaving.
Gotham's in my blood. And I
don't think I can let you leave either.
You re-forged it. Well now.
You see, you say you're leaving.
But I've got a feeling
you're gonna be back.
And I don't like looking
over my shoulder.
Need I remind you,
Barbara. You've already tried
using that knife.
And also, you're outnumbered.
Hmm.
That Demon's Head is really
not working out for you, huh?
(PENGUIN SCREAMING)
- (INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
- (SIRENS WAILING)
Bullock, the hell is going on?
Why are we clearing the bridges?
Because we said to
do it. Now, just do it.
Did a GCPD transport
van come through here?
- (CELL PHONE RINGING)
- About 20 minutes ago.
Had to make way for it.
What's the status?
HARPER: All the
bridges are being cleared.
But I just heard from our choppers,
they've spotted vans on every bridge.
The vans are in position.
Bombs could go off any minute.
What the hell.
HARVEY: Jim.
GORDON: Out of the way.
(GRUNTING)
When will you ever learn,
Barbara? The knife has to be held...
Held by Bruce Wayne. I get it.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(ROPE TIGHTENING)
So you know, this is for Selina.
(GRUNTS)
In that case,
it must be very disappointing
for you to be dying like this.
(GUNSHOTS)
What are you doing?
Well done, Barbara.
(CAR ALARMS BLARING)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
The choice is now
yours. Stay Bruce Wayne.
Or accept your destiny.
Become Gotham's Dark Knight.
(SCREAMING)
(DAGGER CLATTERS)
(EXHALES)
Seems Jeremiah's
made good on his threat.
And I take it that
means you're not leaving.
How can I?
They need me more than ever
now. No one will help them but me.
So, what does that mean for us?
Ed, this is the end
of the road for us.
All this time I've been
calling the other Ed stupid.
And I'm the idiot.
You were never
gonna leave with me.
You just wanted
to save Jim Gordon.
You and Jim really
aren't that different.
You both think you know me.
You both wanna change me.
Neither one of
you really sees me.
(GASPS)
(GASPING)
For what it's worth, Ed, I was
offering you something real.
But I was never going
to be who you wanted.
Sooner or later, you
were just gonna kill me.
It's just what you do.
That's quite possible.
(GRUNTS)
But you're wrong, Lee.
(BOTH GASPING)
I do see you.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(GASPS)
Calm.
Where is Butch? What
did you do with him?
I'm right here.
You're you.
Yeah. I'm me again.
- Yeah.
- I love you.
I love you too, baby.
(CHUCKLES)
Oswald,
I'll never forget this.
Anything you need, I'm there.
Thank you, Butch.
I want you to know I
consider you a friend.
And that I'm truly sorry.
What?
(GROANING)
Did you think I forgot that
you murdered my mother?
That I just got over it?
I have lived with
that pain every day.
I could've killed you
any time I wanted,
but I believe in
an eye for an eye.
You took away the
one person I loved,
so I took away the
one person you loved.
And you get to live with that.
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
All of this...
Finding Strange, curing Butch,
was all so you could
kill him in front of me?
Exactly. But don't worry.
In time, when I feel that
you have suffered enough,
I will kill you too.
Not if I kill you first.
You're welcome to try.
(GRUNTS)
(SCREAMS) I'll kill you!
BRUCE: Selina.
How is she?
She did well in surgery.
But the bullet severed
her spinal cord.
And the damage
is likely permanent.
Mr. Wayne, the
hospital is shutting down.
This is the last ambulance
leaving for the post. We have
room for you, but we need to go.
Bruce.
I can't leave, Alfred.
Ra's was right.
This is what I'm meant to do.
The city's abandoned,
Master Bruce.
There's nothing more
you can do here, mate...
Jeremiah is still out there.
He is not your responsibility.
Gotham is not
your responsibility.
I'm making it mine.
Um...
Oh, sod it.
All right, fine.
- We'll both stay.
- No.
I need to know
Selina's gonna be okay.
Please.
(SIGHS)
All right, I'll see
that she's safe.
And then I'll come
back and I will find you.
I promise.
(ENGINE STARTS)
HARVEY: You just can't throw
in the towel on an entire city.
There's no way to know how
many bombs are still out there.
The power's out, water
supply is damaged.
You're giving up.
Plain and simple.
We're proceeding with the
evacuation. Boats will run all night.
Everyone leaves,
including the police.
Now the Governor's
declared the city off-limits until
this situation can be evaluated.
I'm not leaving.
So, if you're gonna
arrest me, do it now.
(SIGHS)
He's right, Jim.
Governor's given up on the place,
there's gonna be nobody here.
Gangs are carving up turf.
Two hours, this city's
gonna be a battleground.
Hey, what are you
guys doing here?
Yes, this will do nicely.
This is our
territory. You can't...
Now it's mine.
I want a ring of fire.
Ten blocks wide.
If anyone stands in
your way, burn them!
(LAUGHS)
The hell?
No, not hell.
(SCREAMING)
Hell is what's coming.
Penguin says fix them.
What should I do with you?
Ra's al Ghul is gone.
You defeated him.
We have spoken and
agreed. We will follow you.
Wow, I am honored.
(TABITHA GRUNTING)
Tabitha. What happened?
Penguin. He shot
me and killed Butch.
Everything that is
wrong with Gotham,
all the greed, the pain, the
corruption, the destruction,
it can all be traced back
to one problem, men.
Well, I think it is time we had
a men-free zone, starting here.
(MEN SCREAMING)
LUCIUS: That's better.
Much, much better.
Lucius?
I requisitioned one of
Jeremiah's battery bombs
before it went to the warehouse.
Just restored it to
its original purpose.
It is an ingenious mechanism.
I told him we were staying.
Figured we could use some
help with the, uh, science stuff.
And there are
others on their way.
This is our city. You're
going to need our help.
Speaking of, there's
something I need you to do.
(GRUNTING)
Where's Jeremiah?
I don't know!
You see him, you tell
him I'm looking for him.
Bruce.
You're not supposed to be here.
Neither are you.
There's a dozen cops downstairs.
You stayed to
fight for the city.
The gangs are carving up
territory. We're gonna have to go
block by block.
I have no idea what
we're gonna find.
A thing like this brings out
whatever's lurking in the shadows.
(SQUEAKING)
(SCREAMING)
The light.
You're basically daring whatever
is out there to come after you.
Let them come.
There are still good
people out there.
They need to know
we're here, willing to fight.
I remember the night we met.
You told me the
world may seem dark.
But there is light.
English - SDH